<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.nl" -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" xml:lang="en" consensus="yes" docName="draft-mekking-dnsop-obsolete-dlv">
<?rfc toc="yes"?><?rfc symrefs="yes"?><?rfc sortrefs="yes"?><?rfc compact="yes"?><?rfc subcompact="no"?><?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="obsolete-dlv">Moving DNSSEC Lookaside Validation (DLV) to Historic Status</title><author initials="W.M." surname="Mekking" fullname="Matthijs Mekking"><organization>ISC</organization><address><postal><street>950 Charter St</street>
<city>Redwood City</city>
<code>94063</code>
<country>USA</country>
<region>CA</region>
</postal><email>matthijs@isc.org</email>
</address></author>
<date year="2019" month="June" day="25"></date>
<area>Operations and Management</area><workgroup>DNS Operations</workgroup><keyword>DNS</keyword>
<keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>
<keyword>DLV</keyword>

<abstract><t>This document obsoletes DNSSEC lookaside validation (DLV) and reclassifies
RFCs 4431 and 5074 as Historic.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>DNSSEC Lookaside Validation (DLV) was introduced to assist with the adoption of
DNSSEC <xref target="RFC4033"></xref> <xref target="RFC4034"></xref> <xref target="RFC4035"></xref> in a time where the root zone
and many top level domains (TLDs) were unsigned, to help entities with signed
zones under an unsigned parent zone, or that have registrars that don't accept
DS records.  As of May 2019, the root zone is signed and 1389 out of 1531
TLDs have a secure delegation from the root and DLV has served its purpose and
can now retire.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="discussion" title="Discussion">
<t>One could argue that DLV is still useful because there are still some unsigned
TLDs and entities under those zones will not benefit from signing their zone.
However, keeping the DLV mechanism also has disadvantages:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>It reduces the pressure to get the parent zone signed.</t>
<t>It reduces the pressure on registrars to accept DS records.</t>
<t>It complicates validation code.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>In addition, not every validator actually implements DLV (only BIND 9 and
Unbound) so even if an entity can use DLV to set up an alternate path to its
trust anchor, its effect is limited.  Furthermore, there was one wellknown DLV
registry (dlv.isc.org) and that has been deprecated (replaced with an empty
zone) on September 30, 2017. With the absence of a wellknown DLV registry
service it is unlikely that there is a real benefit for the protocol on
the Internet nowadays.</t>
<t>One other possible reason to keep DLV is to distribute trust anchors for
private enterprises.  However it was never the intention for DLV to be used
for this purpose, and DLV has some properties that do not entirely fit this
use case:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>It would be more desirable if the trust anchors for internal zones have a
higher priority than the public trust anchors, but DLV works as a fallback.</t>
<t>Since the zones are related to private networks, it would make more sense
to make the internal network more secure to avoid name redirection, rather
than complicate the DNS protocol.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Given these arguments, plus its use case is fairly limited, and the above
disadvantages to keep DLV, it is probably not worth the effort of maintaining
the DLV mechanism.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="moving-dlv-to-historic-status" title="Moving DLV to Historic Status">
<t>There are two RFCs that specify DLV.</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>RFC 4431 <xref target="RFC4431"></xref> specifies the DLV resource record.</t>
<t>RFC 5074 <xref target="RFC5074"></xref> specifies the DLV mechanism for publishing trust
anchors outside the DNS delegation chain and how validators can use them
to validate DNSSEC-signed data.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>This document moves both RFC 4431 <xref target="RFC4431"></xref> and RFC 5074 <xref target="RFC5074"></xref> to
Historic status.  This is a clear signal to implementers that the DLV
resource record and the DLV mechanism SHOULD NOT be implemented or deployed.</t>

<section anchor="documents-that-reference-the-dlv-rfcs" title="Documents that reference the DLV RFCs">
<t>The RFCs that are being moved to Historic status are referenced by a couple
of other documents.  The sections below describe what changes when the DLV
RFCs have been reclassified as Historic.</t>

<section anchor="documents-that-reference-rfc-4431" title="Documents that reference RFC 4431">
<t>One RFC and one Internet Draft make reference to RFC 4431 <xref target="RFC4431"></xref>.</t>

<section anchor="rfc-5074" title="RFC 5074">
<t>RFC 5074 <xref target="RFC5074"></xref>, &quot;DNSSEC Lookaside Validation (DLV)&quot; describes the DLV
mechanism itself, and is being moved to Historic status too.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="i-d-lhotka-dnsop-iana-class-type-yang" title="I-D.lhotka-dnsop-iana-class-type-yang">
<t>The draft &quot;YANG Types for DNS Classes and Resource Record Types&quot;
<xref target="I-D.lhotka-dnsop-iana-class-type-yang"></xref> refers to RFC 4431 to describe
the DLV entry in the YANG module iana-dns-class-rr-type.  This reference
should be removed.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="documents-that-reference-rfc-5074" title="Documents that reference RFC 5074">
<t>Three RFCs make reference to RFC 5074 <xref target="RFC5074"></xref>.</t>

<section anchor="rfc-6698" title="RFC 6698">
<t>RFC 6698, &quot;The DNS-Based Authentication of Named Entities (DANE) Transport
Layer Security (TLS) Protocol: TLSA&quot; <xref target="RFC6698"></xref> specifies:</t>
<t>DNSSEC forms certificates (the binding of an identity to a key) by
  combining a DNSKEY, DS, or DLV resource record with an associated RRSIG
  record.  These records then form a signing chain extending from the
  client's trust anchors to the RR of interest.</t>
<t>This document updates RFC 6698 to exclude the DLV resource record from
certificates.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="rfc-6840" title="RFC 6840">
<t>RFC 6840, &quot;Clarifications and Implementation Notes for DNS Security
(DNSSEC)&quot; <xref target="RFC6840"></xref> says that when trust anchors come from different
sources, a validator may choose between them based on the perceived
reliability of those sources. But in reality this does not happen in
validators (both BIND 9 and Unbound have a option for a DLV trust anchor
that can be used solely as a fallback).</t>
<t>This document updates RFC 6840 to exclude the DLV registries from the trust
anchor selection.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="rfc-8198" title="RFC 8198">
<t>RFC 8198, &quot;Aggressive Use of DNSSEC-Validated Cache&quot; <xref target="RFC8198"></xref> only
references RFC 5074 because aggressive negative caching was first proposed
there.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>IANA should update the annotation of the DLV RR type (code 32769) to
&quot;Obsolete&quot; in the DNS Parameters registry.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security considerations">
<t>When the DLV mechanism will go away, zones that rely on DLV for their
validation will be treated as insecure.  The chance that this scenario actually
occurs is very low, since no wellknown DLV registry exists.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>Reviewers.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4431.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5074.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.lhotka-dnsop-iana-class-type-yang.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6698.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8198.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6840.xml"?>
</references>

</back>

</rfc>
